會有啲實質嘅嘅建議出到嚟，多謝主席。法案，本會現在恢復二零一五年税務修訂第三號條例草案嘅二讀辯論。審議上述條例草案嘅委員會主席梁繼昌議員會就委員會嘅報告向本會發言。梁繼昌議員。
先生， Acting President， in my capacity as Chairman of the Bills Committee on Inland Revenue Amendment Number Three Bill 2015。
我 wish to make a report on the work of the Bills Committee.
我將 focus on the major issues considered by the Bills Committee.
The Board of Review and Revenue Ordinance is an independent statutory body.
Established under Section 65 of the Inland Revenue Ordinance, to hear and determine tax appeals lodged by taxpayers.
The main objects of the bill are.
第一，要 allow an appeal against a board decision to go directly to the court of first instance on a question of law， by abolishing the procedure of requesting the board to state a case on the question for the opinion of the court。
那係要廢除現時的判決式程序。
第二，要 empower the person presiding at a hearing of an appeal before the board.
要給方向，就提供文件和資訊。
第三ly， to provide privileges and immunities to the chairman.
deputy chairman.
And members of the board, the parties to a hearing and other persons appearing before the board.
and finally, to raise the ceiling of costs to be paid by the appellant as may be ordered by the board, from from five thousand dollars to twenty five thousand dollars.
The purpose of introducing these changes is to improve the tax appeal mechanism in Hong Kong.
，作為以及效率和 effectiveness of the board。
The Bills Committee generally supports the proposals in the bill.
在跨涉 deliberation，成員們已檢討，其中其他議題，擬提出的要件，對於當事人申請向法院申請就離職決定提出上訴，就法律問題。
The proposer threshold for the grant of leave to make such an appeal.
和原因， for not allowing the court to receive new evidence on hearing such an appeal.
我會 elaborate on the bill's committee's deliberations on these issues.
The bill proposes that to appeal to the court against the board's decision on a question of law.
the taxpayer concerned.
或，The Commissioner of Inland Revenue。
是 require to apply to the court for leave.
委員會指出，雖然有支持這樣的要件。
There are views among the taxation professionals, including the Joint Liaison Committee on Taxation.
和香港 Institute of Certified Public Accountants。
那，的leave requirement is not necessary.
The Joint Liaison Committee on Taxation argues that, while the decision of the board is final.
Leave is typically not required for final decisions in other civil litigation appeals.
The introduction of the leave requirement would defeat the purpose of abolishing the case state procedure.
which aims to streamline the appeal procedure.
一些成員，
have expressed concern on whether the leave requirement.
Together with the requirement for the losing party in a tax appeal to pay the cost of court hearings.
會 dissuade 一 party aggrieved by the board's decision from appealing to the court.
The administration, in response to these concerns, has explained to the Bills Committee that with the leave requirement in place.
the issue of whether an appeal against a boss decision involves the question of law.
將首先被 dealt with by the court。
Moreover.
for the appeals to the court against the decision of the labour tribunal.
The small claims tribunal and the minor employment claims adjudication board on questions of law.
leave to appeal is also required.
on the threshold for the grant of leave.
The bill proposes that the court must not grant leave to appeal against a boss' decision.
Unless the court is satisfied that a question of law is involved in the proposed appeal.
and the proposed appeal has a reasonable prospect of success.
或係某其他原因，和諧紳士的正義。
Why the proposed appeal should not be heard?
一些成員於委員會。
Have queried.
whether it is necessary to codify the leave threshold in the law.
given that the court would exercise its judgment on whether there is a proper question of law in a leave application.
委員會指出，有關政黨的觀點，即建議的門檻，為「合理嘅成功前景」。
是高於那for the existing case dated procedure。
and setting the bar too high would at cost and delay in cases where the taxpayer has an arguable basis on which to proceed.
行政已經解釋過，葉面閾值，作為包括在法案中，是由司法機構提出的。
The proposed threshold aims to enable limited judicial resources.
要被 put to their best use。
by filtering out unmeritorious applications for leave during the leave process.
一 similar threshold has been introduced for leave to appeal to the court of appeal against a decision of the Lands Tribunal.
on the grounds that such decisions is erroneous in point of law.
and for leave to appeal to the court of appeal.
從任何決定，或地區法官在任何 civil 訴訟或事務。
在course of deliberation on these issues.
委員會已就相關安排在其他法律管轄區進行調查。
The administration has advised members that in places like England and Wales, the state of Victoria of Australia.
Permission from the relevant tribunal or the court is required for making an appeal against a decision of the tax review authority on a question of law.
as regards the leaf threshold in England and Wales.
It is provided in the law that leave for such an appeal shall not be shall not be granted.
unless the upper tribunal or the court of appeal considers that the proposed appeal would raise some important point of principle or practice.
或有其他 compelling reason for the court of appeal to hear the appeal。
Having considered the reasons given by the administration.
the bills committee has no objection to the leave requirement.
和利幅，如所提議在法案。
先生，議長，建議在法案中，就就訴訟上訴對方的決定，就法律問題而言，
The court, when hearing the appeal, must not receive any further evidence on the case.
委員會已研究過，是否這個要求合理。
Members have queried whether the requirement.
might be unjust to the appellant, and contrary to the principle laid down in case law, that is.
The court should have the decision to admit fresh evidence.
行政已經解釋過，在一個對決議的上訴中。
The party to the appeal can only challenge the board's decision on a question of law, but not on grounds of fact.
The proposed arrangement will preserve the function and the role of the board in receiving and considering evidence, and also prevent the proceeding of hearings from being affected by the submission of new evidence by either party during court hearings.
There are similar provisions in the Labour Tribunal Ordinance.
《小claims tribunal ordinance》。
和《minor employment claims adjudication board ordinance》。
as to members' concern about possible needs for new evidence to be heard for an appeal.
The administration has advised that there are provisions in the bill which allow the court to remit a case back to the board with any direction that the court thinks fit.
In other words, during the course of determining the question of law involved in an appeal.
法院 may return the case to the board if the court considers it necessary to obtain further evidence of facts.
precedent。
律政委員會支持第二讀的法案。
neither the administration nor the bills committee will move any committee stage amendment.
The following part of speech carries my personal comments on the bill.
Mr. President.
我 had the privilege of being a member of the board of review for over seven years, between 1999 and 2006.
The board of review is an independent statutory body constituted since 1947.
under section 65 of the inland revenue ordinance to hear and determine tax appeals.
The law provides that the board shall consist of a chairman and ten deputy chairmen, who shall be persons with legal training and experience.
and not more than 150 other members.
Order firm shall be appointed by the chief executive.
at present, the board is composed of one chairman, eight deputy chairmen and sixty three members.
The board has been functioning as an efficient.
inexpensive and transparent tax tribunal.
在 recent years， the number of cases arising from appeal from a determination from the Commissioner of Inland Revenue on cases relating to profits tax， salaries tax， and property tax is quite stable.
reflecting the quality of decision of the board.
In a nutshell, taxpayers have been careful not to make an appeal to the board on trivial and matters without chance of success.
Between 2012 and 2013, the board heard 67 cases, while there were 46 new cases going up to the board.
在2013至2014。
The board heard 78 appeal cases, while there were 17 new cases during the year.
And as at 31 March 2014, the number of cases waiting to go to the high court, including the court of first instance, the court of appeal, and the court of final appeal, was only eight.
先生，主席，的變化由修訂法案提供，大部份是無爭議的。
and will improve the operation and give sufficient.
但 not excessive power to the board, including first of all empowering the board to give directions on the provisions of documents and information for the hearing.
第二，提供免責給主席、副主席及其他成員，及參與聆聽的當事人，以及其他出庭人士。
And third, raising the ceiling of costs to be paid by an appellant from $5,000 to $25,000.
The amendment which received more detailed discussion during the bill's committee stage.
was the abolition of the case dated procedure.
which currently allows an appeal against a decision of the board on a question of law to go direct to the first court of first instance, or as the case may be, to the court of appeal.
在修訂，leave to appeal會只會被頒發，如果法院第一審已確信，第一。
The proposed appeal has a reasonable prospect of success.
And second, there is some other reason in the interest of justice why the proposed appeal should be heard.
sorry， it should be or rather than and， Mr President， many legal and tax practitioners think that these conditions may defeat the purpose of abolishing the case stated procedure。
而 may stifle some genuine appeal cases.
在澳大利亞，一税payer有自動的上訴權，從行政上訴法庭到法院。
And no leave is required.
從Either the Administrative Appeals Tribunal or the Court.
在英國。
leave to appeal is required for an appeal from the first tier tribunal to the upper tribunal.
although the law provides that any party has a right of appeal.
第一庭 tribunal， in the case of Invita Food Limited。
2014Ks invoked Rule 52.36 of Civil Procedure Rules of Guidance, which provides that permission to appeal may be given only where the court considers that the appeal would have a real prospect of success.
我 consider that the imposition of the pure criteria are necessary.
since the fat matrix is that the number of cases going from the board to the higher courts is never high.
And there does not seem to be an abuse of the system.
The UK case demonstrates that perhaps it is possible that a court in Hong Kong would interpret the term "reasonable prospect of success".
以這有限的 manner， to mean arguable， arguable， which is the criterion accepted in Hong Kong under the current legislation before this amendment bill.
然而， uncertainty remains.
On balance, though, I will not table any amendment, and will leave to the good sense of the court to interpret the relevant provision.
Mr. President.
我會像要引述您的注意，那，的董事是個模範的範例，的個好技術法庭。
和專業會計師都慣於他的運作方式。
Indeed, when I raised this model to many of board members of the Financial Reporting Council.
many of them express a personal view that the board model should be the ideal model for the future disciplinary board of the financial reporting council.
它係獨立、運作和成本有效。
and yet I very much regret to say that many, I say many, in the FSB.
are taking a red tape approach to dealing with the disciplinary function of the FRC.
citing the Securities and Futures Commission as a model.
And yet, professional accountants, Mr. President, are not stop rookies or dealers.
And many of our decisions are technical.
and the doing up.
and and expression of an opinion, an audit opinion.
on a set of financial statements.
係一個藝術，而唔係科學。
而其他專業人士，包括律師和醫護專業人士。
have their own independent disciplinary tribunal.
The least professional accountants would want.
是 to have a super regulator.
which is vested with investigation, prosecution, judicial and enforcement functions.
In short, all disciplinary cases which cannot be settled between the alleged offender and the FRC.
should go to an independent disciplinary board, modelled after the board of review.
我會想勸請財政部長和財政部。
要 reconsider this aspect of the regulatory reform for the professional accountants engaging in listed company audit.
Please do not easily give up a model which has been functioning for over many years, and take a broad brush approach to tackle a sensitive issue.
Mr. President, in summary, I would like to urge my colleagues across the board to support the resumption of the second reading and the passage of the bill. Thank you, Mr. President.
有冇其他議員要發言？
兩萬元。
有冇議員要發言？
如果冇咧，我現在請財經事務及副務局局長發言答辯，局長。
誒主席，我十分感謝法案委員會主席梁繼昌議員。
其他委員、秘書處同埋法律顧問嘅努力，令到二零一五年税務修訂第三號條例草案、下清條例草案嘅審議工作得以順利完成。
税務上訴委員會、下清上訴委員會係根據税務條例規定組成嘅獨立法定組織。
負責審理和裁定納税人提出嘅税務上訴。
正如我喺動議議讀時表示，條例草案嘅目的係透過修訂税務條例，優化現行嘅税務上訴機制，並提升委員會嘅效率同埋效益。
目前有關針對上訴委員會所作嘅決定嘅上訴，必須根據情述案件程序提出過程。
耗時及成本高案，亦影響其他上訴個案嘅審理工作。
條例草案透過取消現行嘅呈述案件程序。
容許針對上訴委員會所作決定中嘅法律問題，直接向原訴誒向原重法庭或上訴法庭提出上訴。
法案委員會就條例草案內有關提出上訴一方需先向原狀法庭申請上訴許可嘅規定及門檻，曾作討論。
我想指出，條例草案無意改變上述委員會在確立個案嘅事實問題方面有最終決定權嘅現行安排。
就上訴委員會所作決定中嘅法律問題，向法庭提出上訴條例草案所定，需先向原眾法庭申請上訴許可嘅規定，只在保存現行陳述案件程序嘅過濾作用，篩除有關事實問題嘅上訴。
根據條例草案所定嘅安排，有關上訴是否涉及法律問題，會先在原狀法庭處理。
條例草案定明，法庭審理上訴許可申請時，會考慮而提出嘅上訴是否有合理機會得直，以及是否有其他有利於。
秉行公正嘅理由，因而應聆訊而提出嘅上訴，我哋認為建議嘅上訴許可門檻適切合理，喺確保有關人士嘅上訴權利之餘，嘢亦都讓司法機構有評。
有評於上訴取可嘅權力，在兩者之間取得平衡。
此外，條例草案定明，原眾法庭和上訴法庭喺審理就委員會所作嘅決定中嘅法律問題提出上訴時。
不得收取進一步證據，或推翻或更改委員會就事實問題所作嘅結論。
除非法庭。
除非法庭裁斷該結論喺法律觀點上有錯誤，則屬例外。
有關做法既可保存上訴委員會收取及考慮證據方面嘅功能和角色，亦避免任何一方喺法庭聆訊嘅階段才提交新嘅證據，影響上訴聆訊嘅進度。
無論如何，倘如法庭喺審理過程中認為有需要剝取進一步證據或事實，
法庭可將有關事宜連同其認為合適嘅任何指示，包括進行新聆訊嘅指示，發回上訴委員會處理。
我哋曾就上述有關法庭法庭程序嘅安排諮詢司法機構，並採納了其建議。
此外，條例草案亦包括一些改善上述委員會日常運作嘅建議，主要有以下三方面。
一，負權主持上述聆訊嘅人士。
就提供聆訊所需文件及資料，發出指示。
二賦予委員會主席、副主席和其他成員以及出席聆出席委員會聆訊嘅人士特權和豁免權，加強保障委員會嘅運作及上述各方嘅權利。
及三將上訴委員會可命令上訴人繳付仲費嘅上限由五千元提高至二萬五千元，以加強對所税無聊上訴嘅阻嚇力。
主席，香港作為國際金融中心，税務制度要有律、要有效運作，必須具備高效率嘅税務上訴機制。
條例草案係優化本港税務上訴機制嘅重要里程碑，司法機構及上述委員會對條例草案內嘅各項建議亦表示支持。我懇請各位議員支持通過二讀條例草案。我僅此陳詞，多謝主席。
現將各位提出嘅待決議題係二零一五年税務修訂第三號條例草案二二讀，咁現在付諸表決，贊成嘅請舉手。
反對嘅請舉手。我認為議題獲得在席議員以過半數贊成，我宣佈議案獲得通過。
二零一五年税務修訂第三號條例草案，全體委員會審議階段。本會現在成為全體委員會，現長各位提出嘅代議議題係。